hey guys Shan this side and welcome to
the next video of spring boot so in
Spring boot I wanted to cover an
exception handling but I feel that
before learning about exception handling
we first need to understand more better
about response and different type of
response codes okay so today I will
cover an in-depth about our response in
a springboard so response generally
consider of three part status code
header and body okay so status code is
nothing but an sttp Response Code like
200 500 Etc we will see header is
something which is an additional
information we can send and body is the
data which need to be sent in
response okay so to send this response
in a spring boot we can use response
entity object so so here if you see this
response entity it's a generic class so
whatever the type you will pass that
type is of this
body so here if you
see if I search for response entity
class in this response entity this
T if you go to the parent class this T
is nothing but a type of a
body okay
so if if you are putting this as a
string then in the body you can only put
a string if this is a particular class
object you have to put the same object
of that class
only so take this as an example so here
I have creating a
simple inside of a controller this is my
simple method which is a get mapping get
user so this get user here the response
entity this is I'm returning it and the
type is string so means my body would
can only be sent as an string so now
here if you see in the response entity
object response entity dot status okay
so this is an static
method I am sending what should be the
status so each status denote a
particular uh like what exactly happened
to your request so for this status I'm
saying that okay request is okay https
status is okay and we can pass the
header so here if you see I am passing
like this you can create an HTTP header
object and inside this HTTP header you
can put a name and value what is the
header name and header value so some
additional information which you like to
add okay and then dot body and here the
body type is your string so here we will
put an string here so I just put like my
response body object on go here so this
is an
string so this is how we can send a
response back from our controller but
here if you notice that so here we when
we are doing response entity dot status
do header dot body so this body should
always be at last right so body should
be last so actually it's kind of using
Builder design pattern okay so here if
you see when I am doing Dot status so
dot status method
actually returning what is a return type
of status is
bodybuilder okay so means it is still
not a
final final uh status which we have to
send then I am doing do header so what
is the return type of header is B which
is nothing but a bodybuilder if you go
and check okay so again this is a
builder pattern which we are using and
when we do dot body so here if you see
the response of the body actual is the
response entity final object which we
actually has to return so response
entity so that's why you can't do like
set
status do body and then do header no
that will not work right so I
think you you already know Builder
design pattern which I have already
covered in my lldd design patterns video
so I hope this is one practical example
where springbot is using Builder design
pattern and that's why do body would
always comes at
last so what to do when we don't want to
add anybody in the response there are
many scenarios like delete use case
where we don't add any any response in
the body or any data into the body so
what we do so here you can't do that he
dot body and do something we can't do
that right so here we can use this
method build so here if you see the
build method actually also Returns the
response or entity and if you go inside
build method you will do see that it
will do dot body and inside it will put
null only so here if you see
if in the response entity if we see
build method what exactly is
doing so here it see that build method
what exactly is doing do body and it
just putting a null and ultimately the
final response which we have to send
okay so here if you see the same method
I am putting dot status do header now I
don't want specifically to put here body
null so I can use it do build so
internally it will uh put my body
null
okay so that's where somewhere you will
see dot build and somewhere you don't
find hey there is no dot build so why so
in that case you can already know that
if dot build is used means there is no
body and if uh body is present you don't
need build method because body itself
generates a response entity for
this okay so now here if you
see just see this one I am creating uh
this is my controller class I am doing
get
mapping now here I am creating an object
new user I have created one object and
I'm returning that object itself now
here if you see I am not
putting response entity here that's also
you can use so what happen is spring
boot internally wrap it it
around your response on entity so
internally it would be like
response entity
user okay so usage of response entity is
not like a mandatory you can directly
return the object whatever you want it
to do and ultimately internally spring
framework will do a wrapping of this
okay and here if you see I am not
sending any status I am not putting any
header so what should be the status by
default status would get set here is 200
okay so that would status will go but if
you have to specifically set an status
you have to use response
entity okay otherwise if you are not
using by default would go 200
okay okay
now there is something called adate
response
body so this is very interesting and
many times this is we don't even uh
consider it right but it has very
important meaning so let's see
that when we return plain string or pojo
directly from the class like here in
this case I am returning pojo
right then response body annotation is
required but now you can say that hey
Shan here you haven't put a response
body here I haven't
put response body here then how it is
working now you are saying there
whenever we are directly returning any
plain string or any pojo class something
then at theate response body is required
annotation is required
why so first of all we need to see why
it required it it is required ired
because it tell to considered value as
response body not as the
view so this whatever the object which I
am returning considered as a body the
response body not as a
view okay so now let's see an
example in the above example we did not
use atate response body as I told you
right here if you see I am directly
returning user and object and here I
haven't used at theate response body I
haven't used it because this at theate
rest controller if you go inside it and
check I have I went inside this rest
controller if you go inside and check it
has this at theate response body so by
default with all methods within this
user controller which has this
annotation with all method this response
body will get
appended okay so you no need to
specifically add this annotation because
in the rest controller itself this
response body is
present but let's say that you are using
at theate controller you are not using
rest controller you are using add theate
controller then will this code work now
here if you see that I am using at
theate controller now I am directly
returning a string okay okay or any
object right will this
work now here if you try to run this it
will throw an error not
found what it not found what is is
trying to search so here you are trying
to return a
string so what since this controller do
not inherit like at theate response body
so by default this spring boot will
considered as a name of a view okay so
spring boot will try to look for some
file with this
name okay and since there is no such
file exit it says that not found maybe
some GSP files right or something so it
tries to render like hey where is that
view present so that's where with at
theate controller you have to
specifically use response body you have
to tell that hey what I am returning
considered as the response body not as a
view
okay
now now we know that response entity
what it is we have to be very clear with
the response codes because this is not
only important for learning exception
handling also and also in your
day-to-day project and from the
interview perspective also this is like
very very important so we have five
categories 1 XX 2xx 3xx 4xx and 5xx so
1xx is very less frequently used to be
honest it is mostly
informational so informational is like
when the client and server are talking
right and server has to send some
information to
client then server use this response
code and it is also called as this is
like a intermittent code so server when
tells to the client some information
this is not the final response this is
not the final response server might
still be
processing and then later it might
return a final response so this one is
just an informational one and it could
be an inm inm response code not the
final one second one is Success which is
like whenever the request is
Success then we use 2xx return code
there are so many return codes I will
tell you 3xx is for redirection when you
want client to look at some other API or
some other resource to get the
data 4xx is like a validation error like
something is not either client did not
send the corre correct data to you or
there is some business logic failure and
but this is an
expected expected failure this request
should fail okay so that's where it's
like a validation
failure this is this 5xx is server error
which is like all this request should
get success but because of some issue at
the server null pointer exception type
cast exception something it got failed
which should not be and we should always
make sure that our component should have
5xx error as low as
possible so I will cover the 1xx at last
so let's start with
2xx so here if you see that request
received from
client is processed
successfully so here if you see I have
added five most frequently used status
SC of
2xx 200 reason is okay so this is mostly
used in get method and post method so
here in the get
method your request is successful and
you are returning the response body so
response body
exists and in the post call when the
it's an ENT call when Adent call mean
let's say that post call one so post
means like addition of new user so now
let's say that new user is added user
one added now again duplicate
call duplicate call is coming now what
happen is it will not insert a new new
row so what it will says that hey it's
an
ident ident means the same row is
already present so it will say 200 means
no new row is created but request is
success and it will return the same data
for this one okay so
no when it is an ident no new row is
created okay the same row is used and
the data is return and it will pass as
okay so during post call Adent call we
return 200 and it guess it has response
body 2011 is created it means created
and it is mostly frequently used with
the post apis request is successful and
new resource is created so when the
first call come post so there we created
a new row in the DB and that's where we
return 2011 means some row is
created okay two 02
accepted so here if it is also most
frequently used with the post request is
successfully accepted by the server but
processing is not yet completed so
mostly like bash processing like export
import we use this so what generally
happen is client invoke an API let's say
add
export now the server method simply
return your 202 this one accept it and
before returning 202 it might have
spawned a new thread some new thread and
continuously processing it now this Pro
uh this task might take some time 10
minutes 15 minutes some exporting
importing huge data we don't know so
it's like accepted but not yet
completed 24 no content is your delete
operation request is successful and we
are not returning any data in the
response body okay if data is returned
in the response body we have to send 200
if data is not returned in the response
body 204 should be
returned and request is successful means
like no postprocessing is happening
everything is completed like Pro all the
processing is completed like this 206
partial content so this is also a post
API mostly used it so generally when you
are performing bulk operations like bulk
addition I am trying to do bulk addition
of let's say 100 users now out of 100
user 95 got passed and five requests got
failed so what shall I tell to the
client whether it's a request is success
or fail then we can tell that hey 206
it's a partial content like
partial it's a partial not fully content
right so this is how we can use 206 as a
partial content Response Code this is
just one
example then we have 3xx which is called
redirection client must take additional
action to complete the request so now
the extion item is on the
client so mostly frequently used when we
migrate from Legacy API to the new API
okay so here let's say that 301 which is
a moved per
okay so now here what happen
is it say that all request should direct
it to the new
URI the old URI which client is trying
to access is now moved permanently so
here I will show you one example so in
this one here if you see
that let me Zoom it a
bit okay I hope it is visible
so here if you see the very simple
controller class I have one get mapping
old get user so this is an old API now
in this case I am returning what I am
returning is response entity set do
status is moved permanently so mve
permanently is your
301 and in the header I am returning
location this is the header name and the
value I am putting the new API value /
API SL new get user this one and inside
this get mapping I am just uh returning
response entity status is okay and body
is Success
simple okay so now here if you
see from the
postman if I am
running if I am hitting old get
user so here if you see I am getting
success now you can ask right hey sh you
are hitting old get user API which is
actually not not their body is empty
it's not returning and status is mov
permanently how come you are getting
status 200 and if you see that the
response is Success which is actually my
new API body actually success so how
come this Postman automatic Ally
redirected me to the new API when I'm
just hitting old get
user so here if you see that when we are
so all the clients know this understand
this status Cotes so when I said that
move permanently means some action is
required from the client what action in
the header I have put a location and the
new API so if in the postman if you go
to the
settings the there if you turn it off
this automatic follow redirects if I
turn it off now if you run it here if
you see do you see any response no what
is the Response Code you got 301 move
permanently
now now in the header this location is
there which actually client
follow so you got it so client
understand this like okay
if 301 is coming
then I have to go look at the location
in the header and whatever the new API I
will follow
it okay then there is something called
308 permanent redirect permanent
redirect and move permanently there is a
slight difference okay the slight
difference is
that in the 308 it do not allow HTTP
method to change while redirect for
example your old AP call is the
post but you can redirect it to get but
in the 308 you can't do that if your old
API is post the new API should also be
the
post but here in the 30 move permanently
this is not the Restriction if your old
uh old
API is your post the redirected you can
move to get also so this method there is
no such restriction but in 308 this is
actually improved and it makes sure that
the post if old is post then new also
should be post only that's the only
difference then very important 304 not
modified so here if you see I'll tell
you where most of the engineer use this
response code
wrongly but let's first understand where
it what is the purpose of this 304 not
modified so client make a get call
server return it with the last modified
time in header so this is the first step
server makes a simple get call some get
call server return the data but along
with the data also send the last
modified time when this data which I am
returning when it was last modified now
client cach the response whatever the
data response it got for the get call it
cach
it now client make another get call pass
this last modified time in header and
the header name is if modified
since okay so client add this data into
the header if modified since so what we
can do is when we are writing a
API right and we want to have this
functionality we can read this header if
modified since if it is present into the
get call what it will do is server will
check the particular resource last
update time with what client provided
okay in my DB for this
row user one it was last updated on
let's say 13th
September and if modified since earlier
which client earlier when it make a get
call is let's say also is 13th
September now let's say that if if there
are no change like the client has the
latest data itself there is no
modification in the DB after
that the server will say that 304 not
modified server do not load all the data
and return all the
data server will simply say that 304 not
modified and client will use its cash
data but let's say that client data has
12 September but in DB it's now updated
and it has 1 September then what it will
do is server will load it server will
process the request as usual and return
the new values so that is was the main
purpose of 304 not modified
but I when I talk with different
Engineers they also used with the patch
calls how they're using with the patch
calls now let's say that you have one
data into a
DB user one name is SJ let's
say now one patch call is
coming now patch call says that hey
update
name to SJ now it our API let's say
update API update user API try to update
the name but before that we have a
business logic that hey in DB whatever
the name we have if it is equals to
equals to whatever the name it is coming
SJ like what the new name whatever the
new name it is coming then don't
update then don't update no no need to
update required right already in DB SJ
is there and also you are trying to
update SJ what is the point of updating
it so generally our business logic cast
this and there we try to send that here
304 not modified but this is wrong 304
not modified this is not the actual
purpose the purpose of 304 is generally
used with the when the client using the
caching and client is also passing this
header and server consuming this headers
if modified sense but never try to use
with the patch like in this
scenario in this case generally you can
pass 20 200 okay like no row updated
nothing right or 204 like no
content okay so then we have four EX X
which is a validation error client need
to pass the correct request to the user
server so the server has failed this
request but it's not a fault of a server
it's either for fault of a client or
business
logic so there are many
popular four XX error codes first is 400
which is nothing but a bad request most
frequently used with get post pass
delete API client is not passing the
required details to process the
request if for a particular
API I need these three Fields if client
is not passing one of the
field
then server will fail with bad request
hey you haven't given me the correct
request itself I need this details to
process the
request 401
unauthorized again popular with all all
the
apis any API which require
authentication so if you see that in the
header when you pass a request certain
API required like some token like be
token or basic authentication where you
provide a username password itself but
if you are not providing those then and
if you try to access that API it will
fail with 401 unauthorized any API which
accept the
authentication and if you are not
providing this it will
fail 403 Forbidden
is let's say you have an API user API
okay now in this user API there is
certain operation there is certain
operation let's say
that if API get invoked from admin if
admin invokes
that then it's okay let's say that uh
there is something called
address address
updation updation of an address can only
be done by admin no other user has
permission for it if if a call comes
apart from admin and they're trying to
update an address
okay then it we will fail it with
forbidden because that client do not
have that permission to update the
address only admin as a client has the
permission
okay then we have 404 not found so here
what happen is generally popular with
get patch and delete not with the post
because in the post we are trying to
create a new row but here uh
404 here in the apis let's say you are
doing a get call you are trying to fetch
certain user 1 2 3 hey get me the
details of this user you are trying to
do a patch hey uh this is the patch
call for this user so now we are working
on a particular ID we are telling a
server that hey I want to do a get on
this ID or patch update of this ID or
delete this ID so what generally server
will do is it will try to find the
details of the ID which you are passing
in a DB in this case let's say 1 2 3 it
trying to fetch but in DB there is no
such ID present what server will do it
server will send 404 not found hey I
didn't found the resource itself what
you trying to look
for okay so maybe client not had sent
this ID correctly
then we have 405 method not allowed so
again let's say that hitting get API but
with post HTTP method so here in this
case it's a get but if I just make it
post what I will get 45 method not
allowed so I have this is a get API but
if you're trying to hit with the wrong
method you will get
this 422 is unprocessable entity again
popularly uh frequently used with all
this methods during get post patch
delete what exactly 422 is that some
business logic failure business logic
failure means that very specific to your
business let's say that France user
should not be allowed to open an
account okay as we haven't got a license
in this country so France user should
not get onboarded
but if any request comes to post for
user country is let's say
France okay even though request is valid
everything is proper all the fields are
set but your business logic will stop
this okay so your business logic will
cash this that and says that hey it's an
unprocessable entity we cannot process
it it's a business validation
actually then we have something called
429 too many
request so here what happen is
that we are putting a rule for example
one user can Max make 10 call in a
minute this is the
maximum calls it can make in a
minute now if user 1 2 3 4 5 makes the
11th call in a minute then that will get
blocked and we throw
that 4 29 too many
request okay so consider this type of a
rate limiting it's a type of rate
limiting we are trying to do that uh if
too many request user is
making okay then your rate limiter will
says that hey not allowed uh so in a
minute 10 calls are allowed right so
okay 1 2 3 4 till 10 calls are all
success in a minute the 11th call let's
say that it says that hey rate limiter
says that hey the 11th call which you
trying to
process this is not allowed now so what
you can do is you can send 429 too many
requests and also there is something
called 409 which is called conflict
actually so 409 conflict is that like uh
you have one
request one request which is already in
in progress It's not yet completed in
progress let's
say/ user1 2 3 any API let's say patch
API okay so mostly 409 conflict is
popular with patch
delete and post not with the get get is
like you can do as many time I get but
this three operations patch delete and
post what happen is that when it is in
progress when it is in
progress and another request comes same
SL user123 same thing exactly same what
it will says
that we return 49 and we say that hey
conflict it's already in progress so
what generally we do is we put a
lock right let's say in some cash or
itself has said that hey 1 2 3 currently
will says that some it is
logged okay so till
this request is not completed this lock
would be there and if any request comes
while this above request is in
progress it would like conflict and we
will return 409 so generally this lock
generally we also put TTL itself said
after let's say 10 second automatically
get released because we know that
seconds is sufficient for a one API to
get completed depending upon your apis
maybe you can put 5 Second 1 second 2
seconds right or if you don't want to
put TTL you want to manually release it
okay request is success and then go and
remove the LW remove this
lock okay so 409 conflict is also very
popular okay then we have five access
like a server error request got failed
at server even though client passed the
valid request means something wrong at
server so here if you see that this is
the most popular like always we send 500
internal error code generally any issue
comes because for us server should not
fail at all when we write a code we
write in a way that this if it's a valid
request all the validations like for all
the 4xx it has crossed all validations
are success then request should get
success so every time we write a code we
write in a manner that if there is
request is proper no business logic
failure user is properly authenticated
has the permission request should be
success but if still it is failing we
don't know man like we are not purposely
writing a code to fail and handle it no
so that's why most of the error goes
into this bucket internal server error
because we
we are writing the code but somehow it
is failing which we might have to debug
so it's that's why internal server error
generic err code when no specific reason
is
suitable
okay 501 not so generally here if you
see the null pointer exceptions are the
major culprits here sometime DB is down
okay so those are the factors which can
contribute to a server
failure then we have 501 not implemented
here what happen is uh API lacks the
ability to fulfill the request so what
happen is sometimes we do uh code in
chunks so now let's say that I have
created this API / API
sluser but the code implementation is
not fully but I have put that a if this
API has been
invoked return this one 501 error code
okay because this implementation I have
not completed yet I I will I will do it
so API is in development in future it
would be available but if uh you are
still calling
it you will get 501 means currently this
API is not completed it's in
development it do not have the ability
to fulfill the request today but in
future yes it might be then there is
something called bad
gateway so ser
acting as a proxy and while calling a
stream got invalid response what does it
mean so for example my application is
deployed behind reverse proxy that
engine X so this is
your engine X and this is your
application okay if engine X is not able
to communicate with my application so
here engine X is uh here working as a
Gateway okay and it is trying to
communicate with my
application but it's not able to
communicate okay because of let's say
misconfiguration of port number or
something then it is eligible to throw
502 bad gateway server acting as a proxy
so this is acting as a
proxy while calling up stream so it is
trying to call up stream my application
but get invalid response like not able
to reach it so didn't get a valid
response maybe some timeout while doing
a
connection and then it says that bad
gateway and then we have one access like
informational which is very less
frequently used so interim response to
communicate resp uh request progress or
it's status before processing the final
request so here one as 100 which is
continue mostly used in post API so what
happen is before sending the request
client check with the server if it can
handle the request and ready so at step
one client add few things in the header
first like what is the content length
what is the content type and this header
also put that hey expect
100 so now when the request goes to the
server request reest server will see
that hey okay in the
header expect is present so means it
does it doesn't have to process the
request now it knows that the client is
just checking so server validate
everything client is authenticated it
has proper permission it has content
type length do proper validation all the
till 4X is so the
the server makees sure that no 4xx no no
error should have come in this okay so
all the validation will be done and
server send that
yes send 100 in the response code that
continue and after that client receive
it and invoke the API without the expect
header and server process the
request so now here if you see that this
100 where this server centered this is
not the final Response Code this is just
an
inm okay so client pass to the server
that hey can
I server check it and say that yes you
can and then ultimately client pass the
request and server send this so this is
the final response
actually so this that's why one access
is known as informational that it is
just an
inm Response Code which server send it
to send certain information to the
client to be honest in last 9 years I
haven't used this 100 continue okay but
most of the other response codes is like
frequently used we have done lot of
migration from Legacy and here so three
3xx is also very frequently used so it's
not like that okay guys so any doubt any
question let me know we can discuss
further thank you bye